Father.
父親
Why… Why do you look at me like that?
為什麼…用那種眼神看我？
Father!
父親！
I see you woke up, Sagiri.
看來妳醒了，佐切
Sir Genji.
源嗣閣下
Where am I? Why am I here?
這是哪裡？我怎麼會在這裡？
We're inside a cave in the island.
這裡是島上的一處洞穴
There is no sign of monsters or insects around.
附近沒有怪物或蟲子出沒的跡象
You were exposed to the toxic butterfly scales and were knocked unconscious.
妳因為中了鱗粉的毒而不省人事
You'd better not move.
妳最好不要亂動
I refuse.
那可不行
I can't let the sinner out of my sight.
我不能讓罪人離開我的視線
You're awake.
妳醒了
Are you alright, Miss Sagiri?
身體不要緊嗎，佐切小姐？
Um… what are you doing?
那個…你們在做什麼？
I'm preparing food.
在準備食物
And I'm mending the torn clothes.
我正在補衣服
I'm supervising.
我在監工
Didn't you say we didn't have time?
你不是說我們沒時間了嗎？
Yeah, well… I've been doing some thinking.
是沒錯啦，只是我在思索一些事
Now that Miss Sagiri is awake,
既然佐切小姐醒了
why don't we all sort out the information about the current situation?
要不要整理一下目前的情報？
And eat what Mr. Gabimaru prepared for us.
一邊享用畫眉丸先生準備的食物
Great idea!
我贊成！
Hey, these are starve pills!
這不就是飢渴丸而已嗎？
I was expecting something better!
我還以為是什麼更好吃的東西
Starve pills?
飢渴丸？
I made them with what I could find around here,
我用這附近找到的材料做的
they turned out rather well.
成品已經很不錯了
Also,
還有
I did some research on the island while looking for ingredients.
找材料時 我也順道在島上調查了一下
Bottom line,
最重要的是
I couldn't find anything that looked like this in the area.
這一帶找不到任何像這玩意的東西
Well, we don't even have a full view of the island,
不過，我們還沒摸清島的全貌
so I can't say for sure.
所以也不能妄下結論
But even if you did, how would you know?
就算摸清全貌了 你要怎麼知道那就是仙藥？
What do you know about the elixir?
你對仙藥有什麼了解？
No. I've never heard of an elixir until now.
沒有，仙藥的事我還是第一次聽說
I was just looking for it based on the picture.
我只是根據這張畫去找而已
What I found while searching for ingredients was about the native plants.
找食材時，我發現那些原生植物
Most of them were a mix of different plants,
大部分都是不同植物的綜合體
but most of them were common plants found on the mainland.
但絕大多數都是本土能找到的東西
Well, there were a few that were unfamiliar.
有少數幾種比較罕見
The Ryukyu Kingdom is close by. It might be a flower from there.
琉球國就在附近，可能是那裡的花
Oh, that's great.
那還真是萬幸喔
What I found interesting was there were
其中令我在意的事情是
some flowers that looked like samurai in flower form.
有些花看起來像那些變成花的武士
No way.
難道說…
Where did the samurais who were sent to this island disappear to?
那些被派來島上的武士 消失到哪裡去了？
If most of the plants on this island are former humans,
假設島上大多數植物 原本都是人類的話
I have a pretty good idea.
那是怎麼回事就很清楚了
What the hell are you giving us to eat!
那你給我們吃的是什麼東西？
I didn't use anything like that.
我沒有用那種東西做喔
Anyway, I didn't see anything like this orange.
總之，我沒找到 長得像這個蜜柑的東西
Maybe we shouldn't be too concerned about the picture.
也許我們不該太受限於那張畫
The words mentioned by the Government, "Tokijiku no Kagunomi" and "Paradise"
幕府提過的 “非時香實”跟“極樂淨土”
are originally words from different cultures.
本來也是不同文化圈的用詞
The stone statues scattered on the island are close to Buddhism or Taoism.
島上遍布的石像接近佛教或道教風格
It may be pointless to worry about religious consistency.
但光是在意宗教一致性也沒什麼意義
What we should consider more are the statues themselves.
我們更應該關注那些石像本身
Does the island have the technology to make stone and clay statues?
這座島有能夠 製作石像或雕像的技術嗎？
If so, who made them?
真是如此的話，那是誰造出來的？
Does that person live here in the first place?
話說回來，那個人住在這裡嗎？
It's hard to believe that people could live here.
實在難以相信這裡能住人
The monsters and insects are too dangerous for humans.
怪物跟蟲子對人類來說都太危險了
And the ecology and habits are a mystery.
而且生態跟習性都是謎團
When I cut one,
我砍殺牠們時
I felt it's muscles and skeletal structure,
能感覺到肌理跟骨骼架構
but not the internal organs and, well…
卻沒有內臟以及…
The genitals?
生殖器嗎？
Yes. I didn't feel them.
對，感覺不到那種東西
So they don't have a penis?
沒有老二啊？
They look strange as well.
外表看起來也很奇特
On top of a human body structure,
在人體的架構上
there's another completely different creature on top of it.
連接著截然不同的生物
How can I say it…?
該怎麼說呢？
I understand.
我明白
The items that the creatures are wearing are also very strange.
那些怪物身上穿戴的東西也非常詭異
The items are religious, but they lack detail.
雖然是宗教物品，卻又做得很粗糙
In other words…
硬要說的話
they are half-baked gods.
就像是半成品的神佛
Both the island and the monsters are like that.
不管是島或是怪物皆是如此
They are horrendous, yet silly.
看起來很可怕，然而卻很愚蠢
They are too unrealistic to be a natural object.
他們實在太超脫現實 不像是自然界的東西
Yet too artificial to be a manifestation of mystery.
可是 以具體化的神秘來說，又太過人為
It's like being thrown into a mandala of bad taste.
感覺我們就好像被丟進 品味很差的曼陀羅畫作中
It's impossible to understand and I don't have a clue how to figure it out.
實在難以理解 也沒有頭緒該怎麼解套
A creature that lives without internal organs
沒有內臟，卻能活著的生物
is itself a clue to immortality.
本身就是不老不死的線索了
I'm beginning to see the possibility that the elixir is on this island.
終於看到島上有仙藥的可能性了
If it is, I can find it.
有的話，我一定能找到它
If I find it, I can go home as a man free of sin.
找到的話，就能無罪赦免回家了
Unless we're already dead somewhere
除非我們已經死在哪裡
and this place is the real afterlife.
而這裡是真的彼岸
That's the last thing we need.
那是我們最不需要的可能性了
As Mr. Gabimaru said,
正如畫眉丸先生所言
it would be better to investigate the ecology of the monster first.
我們最好先去調查怪物的生態
We need to know where and how these monsters live.
必須弄清楚那些怪物的巢穴跟習性
It will be risky, but
雖然很危險
the clue to the elixir is at hand. That's all we need.
但這是跟仙藥有關的線索 也是我們唯一需要的
Sunset… It hasn't even been a day since we got to the island.
日落了，登島卻還不到一天
Sir Genji.
源嗣閣下
Sagiri, return to the mainland by boat.
佐切，妳坐船回本土吧
-Why? -I will take your place.
-為什麼？ -我會負責妳的崗位
The criminal I was in charge of is dead.
我原先負責的罪犯已死
You are not only a samurai, you are a daughter of the Yamada Clan.
妳不只是一名武士 還是山田家的女兒
A woman has a duty to marry the next head of the family.
身為女子，有義務嫁給下一任家主
If I take your place, it shouldn't be a problem with the superiors.
如果是我接手妳的崗位 上面的人應該不會多說什麼
You will die as you are now.
妳現在這樣，留下來會死的
Go home, Sagiri.
回家吧，佐切
This is my duty. It is the duty of a samurai to fulfill it.
這是我的職責所在 身為武士，有完成它的使命
I praise you for your auspicious mindset, but look at the reality.
我很讚賞妳的心態，但看看現實吧
Do you have the strength to cut Gabimaru?
現在的妳有能力砍殺畫眉丸嗎？
And that sword…
還有那把劍
Where did you get that? I'm sure you got it from somewhere.
是從哪裡來的？ 肯定在哪裡撿來的吧？
The sword is the heart of a samurai.
劍是武士的心臟
You have already lost the heart of the Yamada Clan.
妳已經失去山田家的心臟了
Well, in a battlefield, that's one thing.
在戰場上，那不過是兵家常事
But in combat, swords are disposable.
在決鬥中，刀劍也能隨手丟棄
They are procured on the spot.
現場撿一把來用就可以了
Indeed, your swordsmanship is excellent,
的確，妳的劍術過人
but only when you're testing swords before an actual execution.
但那僅限於試刀人實際處刑的技術
On the other hand, what is required here is the art of war.
換句話說，這裡講求的是戰技
Superior swordsmanship doesn't go hand in hand with superior fighting ability.
高超的劍術跟戰鬥能力不能相提並論
On this island, you are clearly not strong enough.
在這座島上，妳顯然戰力不夠
That's the limit of a woman.
那就是女人的極限了
Can she return home that easily?
話說，回去是那麼容易的事嗎？
Senta.
仙汰
This is an island where most of the samurai who are dispatched never return.
來到這座島的武士 大多都是有來無回
Even if you use a boat, I'm not sure if you can escape.
就算坐船，也不見得能夠逃走
We need to get off the island!
總之，必須先離開這座島
We can't see in the fog, but
霧太大了，什麼也看不到
we must follow the Warrior Way and move forward!
但我們必須遵照武士道精神前進
Why are samurai so stupid?
武士為什麼這麼愚蠢？
-What did you say? -Read the currents.
-妳說什麼？ -好好看一下海流
If you act recklessly, you'll only get wet and lose strength.
貿然行事只會變成落湯雞 還白費力氣
Samurai are so caught up in what they don't have,
武士很拘泥於自身沒有的東西
they don't know how to act wisely.
不知道做事要動腦筋
I see! I can learn a lot from you!
原來如此，我從妳身上學到很多耶
Is this the wisdom of the Mountain Clan?
這算是山民的智慧嗎？
My grandfather taught me to avoid wasting anything.
爺爺教過我 任何事都要避免徒勞無功
Even if we were to return from the island,
就算我們能從島上回去
without the elixir, we'll be killed anyway.
沒有仙藥，也一定會被殺掉
I'll convince the superiors, so don't worry!
我會說服上級的，所以不用擔心
Trust in me!
相信我吧
I'll get you home, Nurugai.
我會送你回家，濡垓
Of all the sinners who participated in this,
在所有參與此行的罪犯中
you're the one who deserves to live the most!
你是最值得活下去的人
Oh, look!
你看！
It must be the Government's ship! It's huge!
那一定是幕府的船，好大一艘
We can go home with this!
有那個就能回家了
What the…
什麼…
It's the Government's ship… No, it's not. No way.
是幕府的船…不對，難道說…
Are these all the ships that tried to leave the island?
這些都是之前企圖離島的船隻嗎？
You!
混蛋！
-Don't pull out your sword, you idiot! -Why?
-別拔刀，笨蛋 -為什麼？
Most animals are sensitive to shiny things and hostility!
動物大多都對 發光的東西跟敵意很敏感
If only we had steered the boat back.
要是立刻划回去就好了
It's too late now! I'm not smart like you, okay!
事到如今，說這個太遲了 我沒有你那麼聰明好嗎？
Let's find a boat we can use.
找一艘能用的船吧
Run Nurugai.
快逃，濡垓
If you die, the entire Mountain Clan will be wiped out.
你要是死了，整個山民一族就滅絕了
We don't believe in things we can't see.
我們才不相信看不到的東西
But I can't help thinking…
但我忍不住會想
Is this punishment from God?
這是上天的懲罰嗎？
Hey, if you're lost, I can take you to the foot of the mountain.
你們要是迷路了 我可以帶你們到山腳下
Are you an Emishi?
你是蝦夷人嗎？
If so, let me rest in your village.
是的話，讓我們去你們村裡休息吧
What's Emishi?
什麼是蝦夷？
It is a term for those
那是專門用來形容
who do not bow to the Government
不向幕府低頭
and live in the mountains and fields with their own culture.
並在山野中以自己的文化生活的人
In Lord Tokugawa's reign, they are traitors.
對於江戶幕府的統治而言 他們與逆賊無異
Take him away. Get him to tell us where the other villages are, then execute him.
帶走，逼他交代出 其他村子的地點，然後處決他
This will eradicate the Mountain Clan.
這樣就能剷除山民一族了
I'm sorry, everyone. I'm sorry, Grandpa.
大家對不起，爺爺對不起
It's my fault. It's because I brought the samurai here.
是我害的，是我帶武士來的
I…
我…
I am Asaemon.
我是淺衛門
I was employed by the Government,
雖受幕府所聘
but I cannot understand why they would execute an innocent boy.
但我不明白為什麼要處決無辜的少年
If there's a way for you to live, then you should live.
只要有能活下去的辦法 那你就該活下去
What should I do?
我該怎麼辦？
Should I live to keep the Clan alive?
繼續活著好延續山民一脈嗎？
Or should I die to make up for what I did to my people?
還是應該以死彌補 我對大家所犯的錯？
I…
我…
So then… And…
所以說…那…
And I… La, la, la.
然後我…
Sir Kisho! What happened to you?
期聖先生，怎麼回事？
It's me, Tenza! Do you understand?
我是典坐啊，還認得嗎？
Stop it. It's no use.
住手，這麼做沒有用
We're surrounded.
被…被包圍了
What are you doing, Nurugai?
你在做什麼，濡垓？
If you want to escape, go alone.
你想逃的話，就自己逃吧
I've had enough… I'm done.
我受夠了，我不幹了
What are you talking about? I don't understand!
你在說什麼？我都聽不懂
I've been thinking about it.
我一直在想
Whether I should live or die?
自己到底要活著，還是要去死
I finally understand. This is punishment from god.
我終於懂了，這是老天給我的懲罰
For killing my grandfather and everyone.
因為我害死了爺爺跟大家
I don't understand at all!
我完全聽不懂
So why do you have to die?
那你為什麼要死？
Samurais are idiots, right?! So explain to me!
武士都是笨蛋吧？解釋給我聽啊
The Mountain Clan are supposed to live
身為山民一族
for the people, for the good of the village.
應該為了同伴跟村子的福祉而活
Only I survived.
我卻獨自活了下來
And because of me, everyone died.
而所有人都因為我死了
I don't get it at all! What do you mean?
我完全不明白，你這是什麼意思？
Don't make it difficult.
不要越說越複雜
What I'm saying is…
所…所以說
I told you to leave me alone!
我…我叫你不要管我了
If you don't explain,
如果你不解釋清楚的話
if you don't convince me, I'm not leaving!
不能說服我的話，我是不會走的
I'm getting close to my limit, because I have no stamina!
我快到極限了，我沒有什麼耐力了
So tell me!
所以說，快點告訴我
Regardless of your grandpa and clan,
不要管你爺爺還是一族了
I want to know whether you want to die or not!
我只想知道你想死還是想活
I don't want to die.
我不想死
I want to go back to the mountains.
我想回到山裡去
Then there's only one thing to do.
那就只有一件事要做
Survive at all costs!
無論如何都要活下去
There's a boat over there we can use!
那邊還有一艘我們能用的船
We'll break through here and get on that!
我們要突破重圍，坐上那艘船
Got it!
知道了
You're strong, Nurugai.
你好強啊，濡垓
Thank you.
真是幫了大忙了
Right back at you.
彼此彼此啦
We got away for now, but…
總算是逃出生天了
we ended back where we started.
可是又回到了岸邊
Yeah. I think all the currents around here are made to
是啊，我想是因為島周遭的海流
flow back to the island.
都是往島的方向流
If we don't find the ocean current that goes outward,
如果沒找到往外的海流
we won't be able to return even if we have the elixir.
就算找到仙藥了也回不去
And that monster…
還有那些怪物
it's a different species.
跟島上的品種不同
The stranded ships also seem to be surrounding the island.
擱淺的船隻看起來遍布島的周圍
Those ships aren't just from the last few years.
但近幾年派遣團的船量沒那麼多
Let's wash this blood off and then think about it.
先把身上的血汙洗洗再來想吧
The ship that was floralized came back.
那艘變成花的船回來了
So there must be outward currents.
所以一定有向外的海流
Maybe you're right.
嗯，就是說啊
Oh?
怎麼…
Nurugai… Your body shape is…
濡垓，你的體態怎麼…
quite curvy for a boy. Kind of like… a girl's.
太有曲線了，有點像個女孩子
Kind of like a girl? I am a girl.
有點像？我就是女孩子啊
No! What?! Are you serious?!
不是吧，妳是說真的？
Why are you panicking?
你慌什麼慌？
Turn around! You're a girl!
轉過去，妳是女孩耶
Why do samurais fuss about trivial things?
武士幹嘛總對這種小事大驚小怪？
This isn't trivial!
這才不是小事
I beg you, please turn around.
拜託妳了，轉過去
I like your manliness.
我喜歡你的男子氣概
When we get back safely, be my husband!
我們要是能平安回去 你就當我丈夫吧
I can't think right now.
那種事我…
All I can think about now is the island and stuff. I'm at my wits' end.
光是這座島跟其他事情 就已經讓我的腦袋快爆炸了
I'm an idiot after all.
我果然是個笨蛋
Anyway, let me summarize what we need to do.
總之，我概括一下該做的事情
First, let's go around the perimeter of the island and find the outward currents.
首先，要繞島一圈，尋找向外的海流
That's a must for finding a way out of the island.
那是離開這座島的必要條件呢
And it's too dangerous for the two of us to get past those monsters!
還有，光憑我們兩個 要突破那些怪物太危險
We'll need to find allies.
必須找同夥結盟
When the sun rises, take the boat home, Sagiri.
天亮時妳就回家吧，佐切
This task is too much for a woman.
這個任務對女人來說太吃力了
I agree with half of what Genji is saying.
源嗣先生說的我只同意一半
If you can get out of here, you should.
如果妳能盡早離開這座島 那妳就應該離開
But the other half of me wants you
但另一方面，我是希望
to be here to hold Gabimaru down in case something happens.
妳能夠留下來 必要時能牽制畫眉丸先生
I see…
是這樣啊
Well, it's just my gut feeling but…
這只是我的直覺，不過…
The impression I had when I first saw him on the beach is different from now.
他現在跟在海邊 初次見面時的感覺已經不同了
The other day it looked as if he saved your life.
剛才也是，看得出來是他救了妳
It may be because you have to return as a pair, but
但也許是因為你們必須一起回去
you too have noticed his change, haven't you?
不過，妳也注意到他的改變了吧？
Stay back!
妳退後
If so, it would be
如果真是如此
more reassuring if you were here.
妳留下的話會更加保險
That's my personal opinion.
這是我的個人意見
I see…
我明白了
Are you going to watch me all night like that?
妳打算整晚都這樣監視我嗎？
I'm not going to sleep.
我不睡覺的
I'm taking turns with the other Asaemon.
我會跟其他淺衛門輪班看守
Then, what are the other groups doing at night?
那這樣其他組晚上要怎麼辦？
What a poorly thought-out strategy.
真是有夠欠缺考量的策略
The samurai can only obey.
武士只管遵命行事
-So… -Um…
-所以… -那個…
Go ahead.
說吧
Are you feeling okay?
就是…妳沒事了嗎？
-What? -What's with that look?
-什麼？ -那是什麼表情？
I'm just a bit surprised.
沒什麼，我只是有點驚訝
The poison from the insects spread quickly
蟲毒擴散速度那麼快
because of the wounds I gave you, right?
是因為我打傷妳的緣故吧？
That's why… I asked.
所以我才問的
Didn't you say we didn't have time?
你不是說我們沒時間了嗎？
Yeah, well… I've been doing some thinking.
是沒錯啦，只是我在思索一些事
I also owe you.
我也欠妳人情
Thanks to you, I've cooled down. I've made up my mind.
多虧有妳，我才能冷靜 我已經做好覺悟了
It's too dangerous to rush around in the dark,
在黑夜中亂跑太危險
and if the Iwagakure come ashore, we can intercept them.
石隱眾登岸的話，阻止他們就是了
I've decided to live with my wife.
我已經決定要跟妻子一起生活
A long life with her.
跟她長長久久地活下去
I will not run away from those who stand in the way of it.
不管妨礙的人是誰，我都不會退卻
I will meet them head on.
我會正面迎擊
You are strong.
你真強悍
You're strong too. Even stronger than me.
妳也是啊，比我還厲害
-No, I'm not. -Yes, you are.
-我哪有？ -妳有啊
I'm good at sensing that kind of thing.
我對這種事情可是很敏銳的
Like a mind, body, spirit thing.
心理、身體或精神這類的
The heart just knows it.
我就是能接收到這種東西
I know that you were strong in the prison house.
我在牢房的時候，就知道妳很強了
It's wasn't just an impression, but a more concrete strength.
那不只是種感覺 更是一種很具體的力量
I wonder what that feeling was?
真不知道那種感覺該怎麼說…
You look surprised.
妳看起來很驚訝
Yes, I am.
我是啊
I was told back in my hometown.
以前村子裡的人也說過
If you don't experience it yourself, you won't know how strong you are.
如果不親身體驗的話 就不會知道自己有多強大
You don't know yourself as well as you think you do.
人並不像自己認知的那樣了解自己
You don't know your true self until you act.
直到有所行動之前 都不會認識真實的自己
In the end, nothing appeared.
結果什麼也沒出現
I guess the monsters don't come out at night.
我想怪物晚上不會出來活動
Sagiri, are you ready to go home?
佐切，妳準備好要回去了嗎？
I'll take you to the ship.
我帶妳去坐船
Thank you for your concern.
感謝你的關照
But I'm not leaving.
不過，我沒有要回去
Don't worry about not completing the job.
不用擔心完成任務的事
No, that's not it.
不是這個
This is a matter of my way of life.
事關我的生存之道
That's even more nonsense. You are a woman.
那就更沒道理了，妳不過是一介女流
You're way of life is to return and give birth to a son for the Yamada Clan.
妳的生存之道 就是回去為山田家生下男丁
That's what I've been told all my life.
至今為止，所有人都是那樣對我說
The derisive eyes that look at a woman wielding a sword.
那些看著女人揮劍的嘲諷眼神
People saying, "What are you doing? You're a woman!"
人人笑我一介女流做這種事幹什麼
Above all, the look of disappointment
尤其是我父親
in my father's eyes.
眼中的失望
A woman cannot carry on the Yamada family.
身為女人，不能繼承山田家的劍
Take it easy and live as a woman.
不用勉強，好好做為女子生活吧
If you live as the daughter of Asa the Decapitator,
如果以斬首淺家的女兒生活
you will be scorned by the outside world.
就會受到外界輕蔑相待
And if you live as a warrior of the Yamada Clan,
如果以山田家的武士生活
you'll be shunned by your family.
自己的家人都會敬而遠之
If I leave here, this will haunt me for the rest of my life.
如果我就這樣離開 這輩子我都擺脫不了這些
I don't understand. Women have their roles.
我不明白，女人有自己的職責
It's only natural.
那是理所當然的
I can't stand the way you look at me.
我無法忍受你看我的眼神
What did you say?
妳說什麼？
Please look at me as a samurai.
請把我當成武士來看待
You!
妳這傢伙…
Please forgive my disrespectful behavior,
請原諒我的冒犯之舉
and my way of life.
還有我的生存之道
I know I am weak and inexperienced. It's just that…
我知道我很弱 也沒什麼經驗，只是…
I will not run away from those who stand in the way of it.
不管妨礙的人是誰，我都不會退卻
I just want to at least decide for myself how to live my life.
我希望至少能決定 自己的人生要怎麼過
I am sure that is true for both men and women,
我敢說，就這點而言，不管身分地位
regardless of their position.
是男是女都一樣
Isn't it a natural feeling that all humans have?
是人，有這種感覺都很正常吧？
Please understand.
請你務必理解
I can't bear to hear that.
我真是聽不下去了
That is not the way of a samurai.
那並非武士的生存之道
This island is a battlefield.
這座島是戰場
Women and children don't belong here!
不是女人跟小孩可以待的地方
What?
什麼？
How did you…?
妳是怎麼…
In the battlefield, swords are procured on the spot.
現場撿一把來用就可以了
That's what you taught me last night.
這是閣下昨晚教過我的
You! A sword is the soul of a samurai!
妳這傢伙，劍是武士的心臟
How dare you take it from me!
妳竟敢從我身上拿走它！
Sir Genji…
源…源嗣閣下…
Subtitle translation by: Mel Nishi
字幕翻譯：洪貞韻